Inventory of the Hidayet Dağdeviren collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Large research dossiers, 1818-1951 (Box 25-29)
  - A.II.2, 1908-1910
    - The change of government in Turkey, L'Illustration, articles, 1 May 1909 (Folder 26)
    - The abdication of Abdülhamid and succession of Mehmet V, Saadet, 14 April 1325 (1909) (Folder 26)
    - Sultan inaugural speech at the opening of the Assembly and the sketch of a reply by one of the members of the Assembly, circa 1909 (Folder 26)
  - A.II.3a, 1897-1928 (Folder 26)
    - Strength of Third Army Corps, table, 23 July 1313 (1897) (Folder 26)
    - Commander of the Fourth Army order of the day, 9 August 1328 (1912) (Folder 26)
    - Troop movements, mimeographed table, by General Staff Office, 1 July 1329 (1913) (Folder 26)
    - The territory and peoples which the Ottoman government had agreed to abandon in Europe, clippings, Intikhab-I, 1913 (Folder 26)
    - Military operations at Pinar Hisar and Lule Bargus by Bulgarian press, Turkish translation, 26-27 November 1912 (Folder 26)
    - First Army Müfettişlik orders and reports to various divisions, November 1328 (1912) (Folder 26)
    - The frontiers between Turkey and Bulgaria, mimeographed text in French, circa 1328 (1912) (Folder 26)
    - The military order given to Sedad Effendi, 25 June 1327 (1911) (Folder 26)
    - Second Army Commander General Sevket Turgut letter to the Commander of the First Army on military operations, 21 October 1328 (1912) (Folder 26)
    - Ustruma Army Corps Administrative Council order to the Commander of the reservists, 21 October 1328 (1912) (Folder 26)
    - Military armistice, protocol signed by Mehmet Yaver Paşa and Colonel Tanoff, 14 November 1912 (Folder 26)
    - First Army Müfettişlik orders to different commanders, October 1928 (Folder 26)
  - AII.3b, 1914-1919
    - Türk varliği, nos. 24, 25, and 27, lithographed prisoners of war journal, Cairo, 1336 (1919) (Folder 26)
    - "Hatira-i esaret," memoirs of prison-camp life by Sayyid Basar, 1336 (1919) (Folder 26)
    - Isik, prisoners of war journal, April 1335 (1918) (Folder 26)
    - Irawadi, prisoners of war journal, Nos.1-15, 1919 (Folder 26)
    - Fatwa proclaiming the Great Jihad, October 1330 (1914) (Folder 26)
    - Tasvir-i Efkâr, statement by the Mešihat on the above fatwa, 25 November 1330 (1914) (Folder 26)
    - Fatwa denouncing the Kemalists, 5 April 1336 (1919) (Folder 26)
  - AII.4, 1919-1920
    - Sultan Vahdettin speech, Yirminci Asir, August 1919 (Folder 26)
    - Sultan's speech delivered on the opening of the Fourth Session of Meclis-i Meb'ûsân, 12 January 1336 (1920) (Folder 26)
    - Denunciation of the Ittihat ve Terakki leaders, clippings, 5 July 1335 (1919) (Folder 26)
    - Peace with Turkey, Ifham, clippings, 25 October 1335 (1919) (Folder 26)
    - War of Independence, Sabah, clippings, 29 January 1336 (1920) (Folder 26)
    - High Commissioner of the U.S. at Constantinople Admiral Bristol's report, Vakit, 21-22 January 1336 (1920) (Folder 26)
    - Mustafa Kamal article, Yirminci Asir, 12 August 1919 (Folder 26)
  - B.I.1, 1914-1923
    - National Committee of Denizli, proclamation on the occupation of Aydin by Greek forces, circa 1920 (Folder 27)
    - Ornately designed prayer for the success of the Ottoman army, 12 Ramadan 1330 (1914) (Folder 27)
    - Death sentence against Atatürk by the Istanbul government, Ikdam, article, 13 May 1920 (Folder 27)
    - The Misak-i Milli (National Pact), 28 January 1336 (1920) (Folder 27)
    - Armistice of Mondros, 30 October 1918 (Folder 27)
    - Sivas Congress proceedings and proclamation, 11 September 1335 (1919) (Folder 27)
    - Occupation by the Entente of Syria and Iraq, a circular signed by Atatürk, Sivas, 14 November 1335 (1919) (Folder 27)
    - Commanding Officer report to the Umum Candarma Kumandan on the occupation of Smyrna, 4 June 1335 (1919) (Folder 27)
    - Proclamation to the people of Kayseri encouraging them to resist the enemy, 1 September 1337 (1921) (Folder 27)
    - Statistical table and map of population distribution for Asia Minor, circa 1919 (Folder 27)
    - Atatürk arrival at Ankara for the first time, proclamation, 27 November 1335 (1919) (Folder 27)
    - Adjutant of the Vilayet of Smyrna report to the Umum Candarma Kumandanligi on Greek occupation, 5 June 1335 (1919) (Folder 27)
    - Congress of Erzurum proclamation, 7 August 1335 (1919) (Folder 27)
    - Zabite nizamnamesi, Turkish Railways, 1339 (1923) (Folder 27)
  - B.I.2a, 1919-1921
    - Mustafa Kemal proclamation on the victory at Sakarnya, 13 September 1921 (Folder 27)
    - Announcement by Irade-i Milliaye, 29 September 1919 (Folder 27)
    - Anadolu Ajans and Ogut clippings, 1920 (Folder 27)
    - Information bulletins (4), 25-28 March 1920 (Folder 27)
    - Anadolu Ajans, (5) April 1920 - May 1921 (Folder 27)
  - B.I.2b, 1919-1951 (Folder 27)
    - University teachers and press committee on the modification of the press-law, report, 1951 (Folder 27)
    - Deputies election procedural form, 1951 (Folder 27)
    - Children's party at Erzurum program, 1919 (Folder 27)
    - Military authorities party program, Erzurum, 18 July 1919 (Folder 27)
    - Turkish government note and proposals to the Council of Ministers in Paris, 28 March 1922 (Folder 27)
    - Turkish government note to British, French and Italian governments on the peace terms, 4 October 1922 (Folder 27)
    - Turkish government note to Britain, France and Italy concerning the peace terms, 1922 (Folder 27)
    - Turkish government note to Entente governments relating to the peace terms, 22 April 1922 (Folder 27)
    - Grand National Assembly protest concerning Greek atrocities in Anatolia to responsible governments, 3 June 1922 (Folder 27)
    - Officials and soldiers in Istanbul government, draft plan, 8 January 1921 (Folder 27)
    - Turkish national anthem, 12 March 1921 (Folder 27)
    - Allied note to Grand National Assembly on the peace terms, 24 September 1922 (Folder 27)
    - Mustafa Kamal proclamations on the occupation of Istanbul by British and allied forces to the Islamic world, 16-17 March 1920 (Folder 27)
    - Mustafa Kamal reception after the liberation of the country from the Greek armies, program, Ankara, 30 September 1922 (Folder 27)
  - C.I.1a. Marriage permits, 1238-1934 (1818-1916) (Folder 28)
  - C.I.1b, 1887-1913
    - Action against marriage of a Turkish woman with Persian, 1888 and 1909 (Folder 28)
    - Turk-Iranian marriages, 1890 and 1911 (Folder 28)
    - Legal act of divorce, 1887-1890 (Folder 28)
    - Regulation of slavery, 1273 (1910) (Folder 28)
    - Black slave trade in Red Sea, circa 1900 (Folder 28)
    - Izinnameh, 1900-1906 (Folder 28)
    - Asiret Mektebi (school established by Abdülhamid II for sons of Arab tribal Seyhs), officials of the establishment marriage permits, 1894, 1901 (Folder 28)
    - License to marry, 1913 (Folder 28)
    - Izinnameh for a woman to marry, 1896 (Folder 28)
    - Izinnameh for a man to marry, 1895 (Folder 28)
  - C.I.2-7, 1797-1914
    - Chain of Shain of the Tariq al-Naqshabandi, Muharran 1213 (1797) (Folder 28)
    - Waqf document relating to the Naqshabandi order on property located on Sofular district, 1234 (1818) (Folder 28)
    - Administration Générale des Phares de l'Empire Ottoman Director letters to Hasan Rami Paşa, 17 August 1907 and 23 May 1907 (Folder 28)
    - Navigation statistics, details of sailings, January 1907 (Folder 28)
    - Regulations on alcoholic beverages, 1881 (Folder 28)
    - Abolition of capitulations, clippings from Yeni Ars and Tesvir-i Efkar, September 1914 (Folder 28)
    - Illegal sale of tobacco of which state had a monopoly, record of proceedings, October 1908 (Folder 28)
    - Fishing in Ottoman territorial waters, regulations by the administration of the Ottoman Public Debt, 1902 (Folder 28)
    - Hygiene regulations to monastic establishments, 1918 (Folder 28)
    - Prayers, undated (Folder 28)
    - Şeyhs tekkeler in Istanbul list, circa 1900 (Folder 28)
    - Studies of medrese talebesi regulations, circa 1880 (Folder 28)
    - Religious functionaries and şeyhs salaries, circa 1900 (Folder 28)
  - C.II.1-2, 1878-1921
    - Patriarch of the House of Cicilia, Catholicos of the orthodox Armenians Stefhanos Bedros X letter relating to the conditions of the Armenians, mimeograph, 1888 (Folder 29)
    - Notice explicative sur la carte ethnocratique des pays helléniques, slaves, albanais, et roumains, by M. Henry Kiepert, Berlin, 1878 (Folder 29)
    - Union Nationale Arménienne Union at Kessab letter to the commander of the region of Ordu regarding good relations between the new government and the Armenians, 5 July 1921 (Folder 29)
    - Porte commission for Turkish Affairs draft report on reform in the vilayets where there was a Kurdish population, circa 1887 (Folder 29)
    - Armenian Committees report on the activity to the Sultan, circa 1893 (Folder 29)
    - Armenian hymn of independence, circa 1918 (Folder 29)
    - Aktranik, Murad and Boghros Nubar, Istanbul, 1920 (Folder 29)
  - C.II.3-5. Ls'ihat al-Islah li Wilayat Bayrut from Muntada al-Adabi (literary club), presented by al-Jam'iyyat al-Ummiyyah al-Islahiyyah fi Bayrut, circa 1915 (Folder 29)
  - C.II.6-9, 1920-1923
    - Turkish National Forces Commander Cevdet letter to the Kirkuk Committee (K. Cemiyeti Suleymaniye), Iraq on British policy which is threatening Muslim unity, February 1922 (Folder 29)
    - Köy Sancak Qaimakam letter to National Forces Commander about a mule seized from British army, 1922 (Folder 29)
    - British policy in Iraq, the position of the Kurds, the Armenians, etc. vis-à-vis Great Britain, French and Turkish interests in the area, report, circa 1920 (Folder 29)
    - Fevzi and Renzi Beyler report to National Forces Commander on Kurdish chiefs in Suleymaniye, 1923 (Folder 29)
    - National Forces Commander in Iraq and Mesopotamia Ozdemir letter to Kurdish chief in Rvandiz Seyh Abdulkader urging joint action against British forces, September 1922 (Folder 29)
    - Chief of Ulema of Köy Sancak Mahmut letter to Syrian and Palestine Commander in Ravandiz, concerning an operation against British fortresses, September 1922 (Folder 29)
    - Şeyh Abdulkader statement on Turk-Kurdish friendship, and the attitude of the British against Kurds, September 1922 (Folder 29)
    - Köy Sancak letter to National Forces Commander in Iraq and Mesopotamia relating to "atrocities" of British in their area, 10 October 1922 (Folder 29)
    - Mehmet Mehdi on behalf of Kurdish chief Seyh Mahmud letter to TBMM, February 1922 (Folder 29)
    - Letter to a Kurdish commander on behalf of TBMM in recognition of his services and successes, 1922 (Folder 29)
    - British forces Commander in Mesopotamia letter to Abdullah Aga, Mudur of Tak Tak district, advocating opposition to Turkish forces, circa 1920 (Folder 29)
    - Şeyh Mahmud circular letter to the Kurds against the British, circa 1920 (Folder 29)
  - C.III. General Anton Denikin Government at Constantinople, Department of Trade and Industry, correspondence, regulations, clippings, reports, and minutes, 1919-1921 (Folder 29)
- Scrapbooks, 1883-1885 (Box 30-33)
  The scrapbooks contain newspapers clippings in French, Greek, and English
  - Balkan crisis, clippings with handwritten notes in French, Greek, and English, 1883-1885 (Folder 30-33)
- Oversize files, 1875-1914 (Box 34)
  The files contain oversize documents removed from the Research files series folders by the Hoover Institution for preservation in oversize files
  - Research files, 1797-1943
    From boxes 1-21
    - D60. Turkish affairs, clippings from British newspapers, scrapbook, 1875-1881 (Folder 34)
    - D81. "La Turiquie Constitutionnelle" parliament members, posters, circa 1908 (Folder 34)
    - DE31. Medrese reforms, pamphlet, 1911 (Folder 34)
    - DE38. Army organization, "De l'Empire Ottoman" picture, circa 1900 (Folder 34)
    - D135. Sultan Abdülhamid II, calligraphy, circa 1920 (Folder 34)
    - DE1. La dette publique, Banque Ottomane, Patriarchats, financial documents and clippings, 1905-1943 (Folder 34)
    - DE3. Jihad during World War I, fetras (statements on legal points), Afghanistan, 1914-1917 (Folder 34)
    - D28. Russo-Turkish Wars, 1810-1938, Ottoman Empire map, circa 1850 (Folder 34)
    - D19. Greco-Turkish War of 1897, map, 1898 (Folder 34)
    - AI.3-5. Second Constitutional Period, map of the Holy War, 1914 (Folder 34)
    - D64. German Emperor Wilhelm II visit to Istanbul in 1898, Ottoman naval vessels visual representation, drawings, 1907 (Folder 34)
    - D16. Young Turk Revolution, Northern Albania souvenir in honor of the Turkish Sultan, poster, circa 1909 (Folder 34)
    - D119. Kâzim Karabekir Paşa, detailed map of Tyre in Lebanon, 1909 (Folder 34)
  - Research folios, 1800-1955
    From boxes 22-24
    - AI.4b. Document signed by Abdülhamid, circa 1900 (Folder 34)
  - Large research dossiers, 1818-1951
    From boxes 25-29
    - D58. Balkan War map, 1914 (Folder 34)